<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An antidote against poyson, or, An answer to the Brief notes upon the creed of St. Athanasius, by an anonimous author by J. Savage ...</title>
            <author>Savage, J. (John), 1645-1721.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1690</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 67 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A62254</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S768</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R19099</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12284995</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12284995</idno>
            <idno type="VID">58824</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A62254)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 58824)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 822:6)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An antidote against poyson, or, An answer to the Brief notes upon the creed of St. Athanasius, by an anonimous author by J. Savage ...</title>
                  <author>Savage, J. (John), 1645-1721.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>16 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London? :</pubPlace>
                  <date>169-]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from NUC pre-1956.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Brief notes on the creed of St. Athanasius.</term>
               <term>Athanasianism.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="tract">
            <pb facs="tcp:58824:1"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:58824:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>AN <hi>Antidote againſt Poyſon:</hi> OR, AN ANSWER TO THE Brief Notes upon the CREED OF St. Athanaſius; By an ANONIMOUS AUTHOR.</head>
            <byline>By <hi>J. SAVAGE;</hi> Gent.</byline>
            <head type="sub">Written for the Information of the Illiterate and Vulgar.</head>
            <q>WHoſoever will be ſaved, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore all things, 'tis Neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry that He hold the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Faith.</q>
            <p>
               <hi>A Good Life</hi> is of Abſolute Neceſſity to Salvation; but <hi>a Right Belief</hi> in theſe Points that have been always controverted in the Churches of God, is in no degree Neceſſary, much leſs <hi>Neceſſary before all things.</hi> He that leads a Profane or Vicious Life, ſins againſt a plain acknowledg'd Rule, and the expreſs unqueſtion'd Words and <hi>Letter</hi> of the Divine Law, and the Dictates of Natural Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence; He <hi>wilfully refuſes</hi> to advert to theſe
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:58824:2"/>Monitors, and therefore can no way palliate or excuſe his Wickedneſs. But he that errs in a Queſtion of Faith, after having uſed <hi>reaſonable diligence</hi> to be rightly inform'd, is in no fault at all; <hi>his Error is pure Ignorance.</hi> Not a culpable Ignorance; for how can it be culpable, not to know that, of which a Man is Ignorant, after <hi>a Diligent and Im<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>partial</hi> Inquiry.?</p>
            <q>Which Faith except a Man keep Whole and Undefiled, without doubt He ſhall periſh Everlaſtingly.</q>
            <p>By keeping this Faith <hi>Whole and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ndefiled</hi> muſt be meant (if any thing be meant) that a Man ſhould believe and profeſs it, <hi>without Adding to it; or Taking from it.</hi> If we take from it, we do not keep it <hi>Whole;</hi> if we add ought to it, we do not keep it <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ndefiled:</hi> and either way we ſhall periſh everlaſtingly.</p>
            <p>Firſt, for <hi>Adding.</hi> What if an Honeſt plain Man, <hi>becauſe He is a Chriſtian and a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant,</hi> ſhall think it Neceſſary to add this Article to the Athanaſian Creed: <q>I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve the Holy Scriptures of the Old and New Teſtaments, to be a Divine, Infalli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and <hi>Compleat Rule,</hi> both for Faith and Manners?</q> I hope no Proteſtant would think a Man ſhall be damned for ſuch Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition: And if ſo, then this Creed of <hi>Atha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſius</hi> is at leaſt <hi>an <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nneceſſary Rule</hi> of Faith.</p>
            <p>Then for <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aking ought from</hi> this Creed; the whole Greek Church (diffuſed through ſo many Provinces) rejects, <hi>as Heretical,</hi> that Period of it, <q>The Holy Ghoſt is of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and of the Son<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </q> contending that the Holy Spirit is <hi>from the Father only.</hi> Which alſo they clearly and demonſtratively prove, as we ſhall ſee in its proper place. And for the Menace here of <hi>Athanaſius,</hi> that they ſhall periſh Everlaſtingly; they laugh at it, and ſay, <hi>He was drunk when he made this Creed,</hi> Gennad. Schol. A. Bp. of <hi>Conſtantinople.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>And the Catholick Faith is this.</q>
            <p>
               <hi>Catholick Faith,</hi> is as much as to ſay in plain Engliſh, <hi>the Faith of the whole Church.</hi> Now in what Age was this which here fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows, the Faith of the whole Church? Not in the Age of <hi>Athanaſius</hi> himſelf; who for this Faith, and for Seditious Practices, was baniſh'd from <hi>Alexandria</hi> in <hi>Egypt</hi> (where he was Biſhop) no leſs than <hi>Four times;</hi> whereof the firſt was by <hi>Conſtanti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e</hi> the Great. He was alſo condemned in his own Life-time <hi>by Six Councils,</hi> as an Heretick and Seditious Perſon: Of theſe Councils, that at <hi>Milan</hi> conſiſted of 300 Biſhops; and that at <hi>Ariminum</hi> of 550, the greateſt Convention of Biſhops that ever was. This Conſent of the Churches of God againſt him and his Doctrin, occaſioned that Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Proverb; Athanaſius <hi>againſt all the World, and all the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> Athanaſius.</p>
            <p>For the times Before and After, the cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Reader may ſee <hi>Chr. Sandius</hi> his Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtical Hiſtory: in which the Learned Author gives a large Account, by <hi>what</hi> and <hi>whoſe</hi> means the Athanaſian and Trinita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian Faith did at length prevail, againſt <hi>the Ancient belief</hi> of but One God, or but <hi>One who is God.</hi> Therefore qua<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e, With what Forehead the Author of this Creed, calls this, <hi>the Catholick Faith,</hi> or Faith of the whole Church? when 'tis certain, it has been ſo in no Age, and leaſt of all in the Author's.</p>
            <q>The Catholick Faith is this, That we worſhip one God in Trinity; and Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity in Unity.</q>
            <p>He means here, that we muſt ſo worſhip the one true God, as to remember He is Three Perſons; and ſo worſhip the Three Perſons, as to bear in mind that they are but one Subſtance, or Godhead, or God. So the Author explains himſelf in the three next Articles, which are theſe;</p>
            <p>
               <q>Neither confounding the Perſons, nor dividing the Subſtance: for there is one Perſon of the Father, another of the Son, another of the Holy Ghoſt: but the God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Ghoſt, is all one.</q> Therefore all theſe Articles make indeed but one Article, which is this; <q>The one true God is <hi>Three diſtinct Perſons;</hi> and three diſtinct Perſons (Father, Son, and Holy Spirit) are the one true God.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Plainly, as if a Man ſhould ſay, <hi>Peter, James,</hi> and <hi>John,</hi> being <hi>Three Perſons,</hi> are <hi>one Man;</hi> and one Man is theſe Three di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct Perſons, <hi>Peter, James,</hi> and <hi>John.</hi> Is it not now a Ridiculous Attempt, as well as
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:58824:2"/>a Barbarous Indignity, to go about thus to make Aſſes of all, Mankind, under pretence of teaching them a Creed, and things Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine, to deſpoil them of their Reaſon, the Image of God, and the Character of our Nature? But let us, in two words, examine the parts of this Monſtrous Propoſition, as 'tis laid down in the Creed it ſelf.</p>
            <q>Neither confounding the Perſons, nor dividing the Subſtance.</q>
            <p>But how can we not confound the Perſons, that have (they ſay) but <hi>one numerical Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance?</hi> And how can we but divide the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, which we find in three <hi>diſtinct divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded</hi> Perſons?</p>
            <q>There is one Perſon of the Father, ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the Son, another of the H. Ghoſt.</q>
            <p>Then the Son is not the Father, nor is the Father the Son, nor the Holy Ghoſt ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of them: I ſhall not need to prove this Conſequence, not only becauſe 'tis evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, but becauſe 'tis acknowledged by the Trinitarians. But if the Father is not the Son, and yet is (by confeſſion of all) <hi>the One true God;</hi> then the Son is not the One true God, becauſe He is not the Father: the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon is ſelf-evident, for How can the Son be the one true God, <hi>if he is not He who is the One true God?</hi> After the ſame manner it may be proved, that (on the Athanaſian Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples) neither the Father nor Holy Spirit are, or can be God, or the One true God; for neither of them is the Son, who is the One true God according to <hi>Athanaſius,</hi> and all Trinitarians: for thy all ſay, the Father is the One true God, the Son is the One true God, and the Holy Ghoſt is the One true God. Which is a three-fold Contradiction, becauſe there is but One true God, and One of theſe Perſons is not the other. But if it be a Contradiction, 'tis certainly falſe; for every Contradiction being made up of Inconſiſtences, deſtroys it ſelf, and <hi>is its own Confutation.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>The Godhead of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Ghoſt, is all One; the Glory equal, the Majeſty coe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal.</q>
            <p>The meaning of the laſt Clauſe is, That the Glory and Majeſty of the Son and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Spirit, is equal to the Glory and Majeſty of the Father; or the Son and Holy Spirit are equally Glorious and Majeſtical with God the Father.</p>
            <p>Therefore I ask, Whether the Glory and Majeſty, with which the Son and Spirit are Glorious and Majeſtical, be <hi>the ſame in Num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber</hi> (that is, the very ſame) with which the Father is Glorious and Majeſtical; or only <hi>the ſame for Kind and Degree?</hi> If it be not the ſame <hi>in Number,</hi> then the Godhead of the Father, and of the Son, is not (as this Creed teaches) <hi>all One;</hi> and they are not one and the ſame God; for two <hi>Infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite and Diſtinct Glories,</hi> and <hi>Majeſties,</hi> make two Gods, and three make three Gods; as every one ſees, and (to ſay true) the Trinitarians themſelves confeſs. It remains therefore that, they ſay, the Glory and Majeſty of the Son and Spirit, is <hi>the ſame in Number,</hi> and not for Kind and Degree on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, with that of the Father: but then it follows, that the Glory and Majeſty of theſe Perſons is <hi>neither Equal nor Coeternal.</hi> Not Equal; for 'tis the ſame, which Equals never are: nor Coeternal, for this alſo plainly intimates that they are Diſtinct; for how Coeternal, if not Diſtinct? Do we ſay, a thing is Coeternal or Contemporary with it ſelf? Therefore this Article alſo doth impugn and deſtroy it ſelf. Beſides, if the Glory and Majeſty of the Three Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons be <hi>numerically the ſame,</hi> then ſo are all their other Attributes: from whence it fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows, that there is not any real Difference between the Three Perſons: and they are only <hi>three ſeveral Names of God;</hi> which is the Hereſie of the Sabellians.</p>
            <p>In the next place this Creed teaches, that <q>The Father is Incomprehenſible, Uncreate, Eternal, Almighty; the Son is Incomprehenſible, Uncreate, Eternal, Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty; the Holy Spirit is Incomprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, Uncreate, Eternal, Almighty: Alſo that each of theſe Perſons <hi>by himſelf</hi> is God and Lord; ſo that the Father is God, the Son is God, and the Holy Ghoſt is God: yet there are not Three Gods or Lords, nor Three Incomprehenſibles, nor Three All mighties, nor Three Eternals or Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>created.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Now if in imitation of this, a Man ſhould
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:58824:3"/>have a mind to ſay; <q>The Father is a Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, the Son is a Perſon, and the Holy Ghoſt is a Perſon; yet <hi>not three Perſons,</hi> but one Perſon.</q> I would know, why this were not as good <hi>Grammar and Arithme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick;</hi> as when <hi>Athanaſius</hi> ſays, the Father is God, the Son is God, and the Holy Ghoſt is God, yet <hi>not three Gods,</hi> but one God: or when He ſays, the Father Uncreated, the Son Uncreated, and the Holy Ghoſt Uncrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, yet <hi>not three vncreated,</hi> but one Uncrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted; and ſo of the reft?</p>
            <p>Doth not a Man contradict himſelf, when the Term or Terms in his Negation, are the ſame with thoſe in his Affirmation? If not, then it may be true, that <q>the Father is a Perſon, the Son is a Perſon, the Holy Ghoſt is a Perſon, yet <hi>there are not Three Perſons,</hi> but One Perſon;</q> For all the fault here is only this, that in the laſt Clauſe the term <hi>Perſon</hi> is <hi>denied</hi> to belong to more than One, when in the firſt it had been <hi>Affirmed</hi> of no fewer than Three. For the ſame Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon it muſt be a Contradiction to ſay, <q>The Father is God, the Son is God and the H. Ghoſt is God, yet <hi>there are not three Gods,</hi> but one God;</q> For the Term <hi>God</hi> is at laſt, <hi>denied</hi> to belong to more than One, though in the firſt Clauſe it was <hi>affirmed</hi> of Three, Will they ſay that in theſe words, <hi>there are not three Gods, but one God;</hi> the Term <hi>God</hi> is not Denied to belong to more than One, or is not appropriated to One? If ſo, then <hi>there are not three Perſons, but one Perſon; and</hi> again <hi>There are not three Men, but one Man;</hi> Then, I ſay, theſe Propoſitions do not Deny the Terms <hi>Perſon</hi> and <hi>Men</hi> to belong to more than One, or appropriate them to One only; which yet every Body confeſſes they do.</p>
            <p>But here is a <hi>Numerical,</hi> or Arithmetical, as well as Grammatical Contradiction. For in ſaying, God the Father, God the Son, and God the Holy Ghoſt; yet not Three Gods, but One God; A Man firſt diſtinctly, numbers Three Gods; and then in ſumming them up, <hi>bruitiſhly</hi> ſays, not Three Gods, but One God.</p>
            <p>To theſe things it will perhaps be an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, that when we ſay, <hi>God the Father, God the Son, and God the Holy Ghoſt;</hi> or thus, <hi>The Father is God, the Son is God, and the Holy Ghoſt is God;</hi> the Term <hi>God</hi> is uſed Eſſentially, and therefore comprehends the whole Three Perſons; ſo that there is nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>a Grammatical, nor Arithmetical Contradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.</hi> But this Remedy is worſe (if poſſible) than the Diſeaſe; for it owns that there are <hi>Three Perſonal Gods,</hi> though there is but <hi>one Eſſential God;</hi> and that otherways the Propoſitions of which we are ſpeaking, would imply all the aforeſaid Contradicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. This Remedy, I ſay, is worſe than the Diſeaſe; for, 1. Three Perſonal Gods, and one Eſſential God, make Four Gods, if the Eſſential God be not the ſame with the Perſonal Gods; and though He is the ſame with them, yet ſince they are not the ſame with one another, but diſtinct, it follows that there are Three Gods, that is, Three Perſonal Gods. 2. It introduces <hi>two ſorts of True Gods,</hi> Three Perſonal, and one Eſſential. But the Chriſtian Religion knows and owns but one True and moſt High God, of any ſort. And I would know of the Trinitarians, whether they dare ſay, in expreſs words, <hi>There are two ſorts of True Gods?</hi>
            </p>
            <q>For like as we are <hi>compelled</hi> by the Chriſtian Verity, to acknowledge every Perſon <hi>by himſelf</hi> to be Lord and God, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>By the Chriſtian Verity I ſuppoſe is meant, the Sacred Books which contain the Chriſtian Religion; that is, the Books of the Old and New Teſtament. But do theſe Books, and do's this <hi>Verity</hi> compel us to the acknowledgment of three Perſons, each of which is <hi>by Himſelf</hi> Supream God and Lord, and yet all of them together but one God? Doth, I ſay, the Holy Scripture <hi>compel us</hi> to this contradictory Acknowledgment? Is there any Text alledged from Scripture, which all the Unitarians, and ſome or other of the moſt Learned Trinitarians, do not eaſily interpret in ſuch ſenſe, that the Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of God is preſerved; and no more than one Perſon (even the God and Father of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt) acknowledged to be God? See the Hiſtory of the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nitarians.</hi> But if there is no Text of Scripture, but what is in the Opinion of ſome or other of their own Learned Men, fairly capable of a ſenſe contrary to the Faith deliver'd in this Creed;
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:58824:3"/>then we are <hi>not compelled</hi> to acknowledg this Faith. And the truth is, the Conteſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the Unitarians and Trinitarians is not, as is commonly thought, <hi>a Claſh of Reaſon with Scripture:</hi> but it layeth here, Whether, when the Holy Scriptures may be underſtood as teaching only one God, or but One who is God, which agrees with the reſt of Scripture, and with Natural Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon; we muſt notwithſtanding, prefer an Interpretation of it that is Abſurd, and contrary to it ſelf, to Reaſon, and to the reſt of Scripture, ſuch as the Trinitarian Interpretation (expreſt in this Creed) ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears to be? In a word, the Queſtion only is, whether we ought to interpret Holy Scripture when it ſpeaks of God, <hi>accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to Reaſon,</hi> or not; that is, like Fools, or like Wiſe Men?</p>
            <q>The Son is of the Father alone; not Made, nor Created, but Begotten.</q>
            <p>Here, and in the next period, <hi>Athanaſius</hi> is got into his Altitudes, or Profundities, which you will. Here 'tis that the Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant think, they are taught the Inmoſt Secrets of Theological Knowledge; but <hi>High</hi> and <hi>Low</hi> are not more contrary, than the things which are here affirmed as equal Truths.</p>
            <p>If the Creed-maker had ſpoke here of the Generation of the Son by the Divine Power on the Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> it would have been true that, <hi>the Son is neither Made, nor Created, but Begotten;</hi> but then the firſt part of the Article would be falſe, that <hi>the Son is of the Father alone;</hi> for He that has a Father, and a Mother, is <hi>of Both.</hi> But ſince he ſpeaks of the (pretended) Eternal Generation, the latter part of the Article is falſe, and inconſiſtent with the firſt part of it. Every Novice in Gram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mar, and proper ſpeaking, knows, that <hi>Begotten,</hi> when 'tis diſtinguiſhed from <hi>Made</hi> and <hi>Created,</hi> always ſuppoſes two Parents, a Mother as well as Father; 'tis therefore a Contradiction to ſay, <hi>the Son is of the Father alone, not Made, nor Created, but Begotten;</hi> for if He is Begotten, He cannot be of the Father alone; and if He is of the Father alone, He is not begotten, but <hi>either Made, or Created.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>The Holy Ghoſt is of the Father and of the Son; neither Made, nor Created, nor Begotten, but Proceeding,</q>
            <p>The firſt Fault here is, that the Holy spirit is ſaid to proceed from the Father <hi>and from the Son.</hi> To which Hereſie the Greek Church have ever oppoſed thoſe clear words, John 15.26. <hi>When the Comforter is come, whom I will ſend unto you</hi> from the Father; <hi>even the Spirit of Truth</hi> which Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded from the Father, <hi>He ſhall teſtify of me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, He ſaith here, that the Holy Ghoſt is <hi>not Begotten, but Proceeding;</hi> He adds ſhortly after, that <hi>He who will be ſaved, muſt thus think of the Trinity;</hi> Therefore ſurely <hi>Begotten</hi> and <hi>Proceeding</hi> differ very much, and very clearly; elſe tis an Harſh Sentence, that we ſhall be damned if we do not Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive, beſides all other unconceivable My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries of this Creed, that the Holy Ghoſt is <hi>not Begotten,</hi> but <hi>Proceeds.</hi> Yet after all 'tis now confeſſed by the moſt Learned Trinitarians, that Begotten and Proceeding differ nothing at all; and that it is right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſaid, <hi>The Son proceeds from the Father,</hi> and that <hi>the Holy Ghoſt is generated of Both;</hi> directly contrary to this Creed. It follows that <hi>Athanaſius</hi> has damned the whole World, for not diſtinguiſhing where no Diſtinction can be made, at leaſt with any certainty. And perhaps this Damning Humour of his, has <hi>juſtly</hi> provoked ſome to write him, not S. <hi>Athanaſius,</hi> but (draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the <hi>S.</hi> a little nearer) <hi>Sathanaſius.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>So there is one Father, not Three Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers; one Son, not three Sons; one Holy Ghoſt, not three Holy Ghoſts.</q>
            <p>In conſiſtence with what goes before, He ſhould have ſaid, Two Fathers; Two Sons; and Three Holy Ghoſts, or Spirits. For the Second Perſon is the Son of the Firſt; and the Third proceeds (which is nothing elſe but <hi>is Generated</hi>) from the Firſt and Second, which makes Two Fathers and Two Sons and all Three of them are Holy Spirits; for the Father is an Holy Spirit, and ſo is the Son, no leſs than the Third Perſon. But this is not the firſt time in this Creed, that <hi>Athanaſius</hi> has diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered <hi>He could not count.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>In this Trinity, none is Afore or Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter other; none is Greater, or Leſs than another.</q>
            <p>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:58824:4"/>Yet the Son himſelf ſaith, <hi>John</hi> 14.28. <hi>My Father is Greater than I.</hi> And for the other clauſe, <hi>None is Afore or After other;</hi> 'tis juſt as true as that there is no difference at all between Afore and After. I ask, Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Son doth not, <hi>as He is a Son,</hi> derive both Life and Godhead from the Father? All Trinitarians grant, He do's; ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing themſelves on the <hi>Nicene</hi> Creed, which expreſly calls the Son, <hi>God of God, Light of Light, very God of very God; Begotten, not Made.</hi> But if the Father gave to the Son Life and Godhead; He muſt have both before he could communicate or give either of them to the Son, and conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly was afore the Son was. No Effect is ſo early as its Cauſe; for if it were, it ſhould not have needed, or had that for its Cauſe. No Propoſition in <hi>Euclid</hi> is more certain or evident than this.</p>
            <q>The right Faith is, That we believe and confeſs, that our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, the Son of God, is both God and Man.</q>
            <p>Then the Lord Chriſt is <hi>two Perſons.</hi> For as He is God, He is the ſecond Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the (pretended) Trinity; and as He is Man (<hi>a perfect Man,</hi> as this Creed afterwards ſpeaks) He is alſo a Perſon; for a Rational Soul, vitally united to an Human Body, is a Perſon, if there be any ſuch thing as Perſon upon Earth; nay, 'tis the only thing upon Earth that is a Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon. Let the <hi>Athanaſians</hi> therefore either ſay, that the Lord Chriſt is <hi>Two Perſons;</hi> which is the Hereſie of <hi>Neſtorius,</hi> condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in a General Council; Or, that He is <hi>not a Man,</hi> contrary to 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.5. <hi>There is one God, and one Mediator between God and Men, the Man Jeſus Chriſt;</hi> Or, that He is <hi>not God,</hi> which is the Truth.</p>
            <q>Who, altho' He be God and Man; yet He is not two, but one Chriſt. One, not by converſion of the Godhead into Fleſh, but by taking of the Manhood into God; One, not by Confuſion of Subſtance, but by Unity of Perſon.</q>
            <p>But becauſe theſe words, <hi>One by taking of the Manhood into God, not by converſion of the Godhead into Fleſh;</hi> And again, <hi>One, not by Confuſion of Subſtance, but <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity of Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon;</hi> cannot readily be underſtood by them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves: the Creed-Maker explains them in this following Article; <hi>For as the reaſonable Soul and Fleſh is one Man; ſo God and Man is one Chriſt;</hi> That is, as a Soul united vitally to a Body, maketh one Perſon, called Man, without confounding the two Subſtances of the Soul and body; for the Soul re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains what it was, and ſo alſo does the Body; So God the Son being united to a reaſonable Soul, and Body, doth, <hi>together with them,</hi> make one Perſon, called Chriſt, without confounding the Subſtances of the Divinity or Humanity; for the Divinity remains, without the leaſt Change, what it was, and ſo doth the Humanity, or rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable Soul and Body. This is the only Offer at Senſe that is to be found in this whole Creed; but ſo far from explicating, that it farther perplexes the Difficulty of the (pretended) Incarnations; as will ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear by thoſe two Conſiderations.</p>
            <p n="1">1. In the <hi>Perſonal <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion</hi> of a Soul with a Body, the Union is between two finite things; but in the (pretended) <hi>Perſonal <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> of God to Man and Man to God, the Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is between Finite and Infinite; which (on the Principles of the Trinitarians) is impoſſible. For we muſt either ſuppoſe, that Finite and Infinite are Commenſurate, that is, equal; which every one knows is falſe; or that the Finite is united but to ſome part of the Infinite, and <hi>is disjoyned from the reſt;</hi> which all Trinitarians deny and abhor.</p>
            <p>You will ſay, If they admit neither of theſe. how do they ſhew the Poſſibility of the Incarnation, or Union of God to Man? They tell you, God indeed is Infinite, and every reaſonable Soul and Body (even that of Chriſt) is Finite; yet the whole God and whole Man are united; becauſe, <hi>As the whole Eternity of God doth coexiſt to a moment of Time; ſo the whole Immenſity of God is in every Mathematical Point of Space.</hi> The very Truth is, they cannot otherways de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend the Incarnation, or <hi>Perſonal <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion</hi> of an infinite God to a finite Man; but with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al it muſt be owned, that then the Doctrins of the Trinity and Incarnation do infer, imply, and ſuppoſe all the Contradictions that Mr. <hi>Johnſon</hi> has objected to the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrin
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:58824:4"/>of Tranſubſtantiation, in that little Golden Tract, ſo deſervedly eſteemed by All. His whole Book, and all his Demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrations are founded on theſe two <hi>Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions,</hi> that <hi>a longer time doth not all of it coexiſt to a ſhorter;</hi> nor is <hi>a greater Extenſion conſtipated or contained in a leſs,</hi> much leſs in a Mathematical Point. Therefore all his Books, and all that he hath ſo well ſaid and argued in the Preface concerning the Authority and Judicature of Reaſon in Matters of Religion, equally and effectual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deſtroys the Ductrins of the Trinity and Tranſubſtantiation. If the Reader would have an excellent Book, let him procure that. But Oh! were the Preſs as free for the Unitarians as 'tis for other Proteſtants; how eaſily would they make it appear, that the Follies and Contradictions ſo juſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly charged on the Tranſubſtantiation, are neither for Number, Conſequence, nor Clearneſs any way comparable, to thoſe implied in the <hi>Athanaſian</hi> Creed, and that the Trinity hath the ſame (and no other) Foundation with the Tranſubſtantiation, ſo that we muſt of neceſſity admit both or neither? If <hi>the Church</hi> is to interpret Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture for us, we muſt admit both; but if <hi>Reaſon,</hi> we can admit neither, and this (I think) the Trinitarians will not deny.</p>
            <p>But ſecondly, In the (pretended) In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carnation or Union of God with Man, the Union cannot be Perſonal, as 'tis between the Soul and Body; it cannot I mean, be ſuch an Union as to make but one Perſon. The Union of the Soul and Body may be properly Perſonal, that is, may conſtitute or make one Perſon; becauſe 'tis not the Union of two Perſons, but only of one Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon (the Soul) to a thing otherways without Life, Reaſon, Memory, or Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>will. The Body is but as it were the Garment of the Soul, and is wholly acted by it, and depending on it. But in the (pretended) Union of God with a Man, there are two diſtinct and very different Lives, Memories, Reaſons, and Free-Wills; which utterly deſtroys a Perſonal Union; for that ſuppoſes but one Life, one Reaſon, one Memory, one Free-Will; for if theſe things which conſtitute a Perſon, are ſound more than once, there is no longer one Perſon but two, and conſequently no Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonal Union in the ſenſe of which we are ſpeaking.</p>
            <q>This is the Catholick Faith, which except a Man believe faithfully, he cannot be ſaved.</q>
            <p>By believing, <hi>Athanaſius</hi> doth not mean bare believing, but he includeth alſo there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in <hi>Profeſſion;</hi> for, He ſaith, a little before, <hi>The right Faith is, that we Believe and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs,</hi> &amp;c. So that a Man cannot be ſaved, unleſs he Believes and Profeſſes as this Creed directs him.</p>
            <p>Firſt, for <hi>Believing. What if a Man can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not believe it?</hi> Are we obliged, under the Penalty of the loſs of Salvation, to believe it, whether we can or no? Doth God re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire of any Man an <hi>impoſſible Condition,</hi> in order to Salvation?</p>
            <p>Secondly, As to profeſſing under pain of Damnation. <hi>What if it be againſt a Man's Conſcience to profeſs it?</hi> The Scripture ſaith, <hi>Whatſoever is not of Faith, is Sin;</hi> if there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore a Man profeſs againſt his Conſcience, He ſins; and if notwithſtanding this, a Man muſt either Profeſs, or be Damned, then God requires <hi>ſome Me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> to ſin in order to their Salvation: but this we are ſure is falſe, and therefore that the Menace in the Artide is vain.</p>
            <p>And now I appear to all Men, that have any freedom of Judgment remaining; Whether this Creed is fit to be retained in any Chriſtian, much leſs Proteſtant and reformed Church? Since it ſubverts the Foundations, not only of Chriſtianity, but of all Religion, that is to ſay, Reaſon and Revelation; there being no Principle in Reaſon and Scripture more evident, than that <hi>God is One;</hi> or that there is one Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty, only-Wiſe and Good Perſon, or Father of all. If we cannot be ſure of this, then Religion and Chriſtianity are built up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Fancy only, and have no ſolid Founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>This Creed may be profeſs'd by the Roman Political Church; becauſe it gives countenance to their Abſurd Tranſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiation, and Cunning Traditions added to
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:58824:5"/>Scripture; as thoſe Doctrins do to the gaining of Veneration, and conſequently Dominion and Riches to their Clergy; But in a eformed Church, where the Scripture is held to be <hi>a Compleat Rule</hi> of Faith and Manners, and alſo to be <hi>Clear and Plain</hi> in all things neceſſary to Salvation, even to the meaneſt Underſtanding, that reads it or hears it with Sobriety and Attention; ſuch a Confeſſion of Faith is (I think) intole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, as being utterly inconſiſtent with thoſe Principles, and reducing us back to the Roman Bondage.</p>
            <p>Beſides, Nothing has been or is more ſcandalous to Jews and Mahometans, than his Creed, the chief Article of whoſe Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion is, that there is <hi>one only God.</hi> The evidence of which Principle is ſuch in nature as well as Scripture, that it has propagated Mahomatiſm among greater Numbers, than at this day own Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity; for the ſake of that one Truth, ſo many Nations have ſwallowed all the Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors and Follies of the <hi>Alchoran,</hi> or Book of <hi>Mahomet;</hi> as on the other Hand, Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity has been rejected and deteſted a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them, on the account of the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans <hi>Three Perſons, who are ſeverally and each of them God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But the Miſchiefs of this Creed do not ſtay here, it is levelled not only againſt the True Faith, but is deſtructive of that Love and Charity, Which is the Spirit and Life of Chriſtianity; and without which, Faith is but a Life-leſs Body. For as if it would effectually inſpire all its Believers, with a Spirit of Judging, Damning, and Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charitableneſs; it pronounces the Sentence of Eternal Damnation, in the Beginning, Middle and Concluſion, upon all that do not both Believe and Profeſs this Faith, and keep it whole and undefiled; that is, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the whole Greek Church, and other Churches in the Eaſt; and upon at leaſt Five Parts of Six of all that profeſs Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity in the World, whoſe Underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing cannot poſſibly reach to the Senſe and Coherence, which ſome pretend to find in this Creed.</p>
            <p>Thus the Chriſtian Religion is deſtroyed, in both the Eſſential Parts of it, Faith and Love. Hence have proceeded many and endleſs Controverſies, bitter Animoſities, cruel Perſecutions, Wars among Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans; and at length the more Fierce and Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olent, the more Deceitful and Sophiſtical Parts, have attained their Tyrannical Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation over their Oppoſers; and have Intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced and ſetled, a Chriſtianity ſhall I call it, or, <hi>a Superſtition,</hi> or <hi>a Polity,</hi> quite contrary to the Doctrin and Practice of our Bleſſed Lord, and of his Apoſtles?</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>An Anſwer to an Anonimous Pamphleteer, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>A Paper fell lately into my hands, which upon peruſual, I found to be and Invective againſt the Perſon of St. <hi>Athanaſius,</hi> and the Author of it a profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Enemy to thoſe Myſteries contain'd in his Creed, which he impugns; and fearing left this ſhould prove a ſtumbling-block to ſome of the Illiterate Vulgar, to ſee the chief Myſteries of Chriſtianity, to be ſo openly attack'd by one who denies the Trinity, the Incarnation of the Divine Word, and the Divinity of Chriſt; and yet aſſerts the Scriptures, the Old and New Teſtament, to be the Word of God: I reſolved to anſwer the Arguments of this Deift, which I here undertake.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="9" facs="tcp:58824:5"/>And becauſe this Author hath involved himſelf in obſcurity and confuſion, I ſhall endeavour by ſome previous Obſervations, to clear the way to this Diſcourſe in a Matter ſo difficult and nice, and ſo remote from Senſe; by this means not to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found the Reader, but to render the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe ſo clear and conſpicuous, as the Nature of theſe Sublime Myſteries are capable of; where I ſhall wave thoſe In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignities and Aſperſions which this Author caſts upon the Perſon of St. <hi>Athanaſius,</hi> leaving this to the Learned Hiſtorians, and confine my ſelf wholly to the Scope of ſuch Dogmatical Principles as he endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours to ſubvert.</p>
               <p>My firſt Obſervation is the nature of the Myſtery of the Sacred Trinity,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Obſervation.</hi>
                  </note> wherein all Orthodox Chriſtians hold as an <hi>Article of Faith,</hi> one only God, and Three Divine Perſons, <hi>(viz.)</hi> the Father, Son, and Holy Ghoſt, by a real Identity between the Divine Nature, and the Perſonality of theſe Three Perſons, ſo that the Divinity or God-head is ſingular, and indiviſible; but the Perſonalities are really diſtinct from each other, and yet really identified with the Divine Eſſence, ſo that all toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther make <hi>unum ſummum Ens,</hi> as the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil of <hi>Lateran</hi> terms it.</p>
               <p>A ſecond Obſervation is.<note place="margin">2 <hi>Obſervation.</hi>
                  </note> that there are three man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners of ſpeaking in this Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Myſtery, which ought ſtrictly to be obſerv'd.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Some expreſſions are abſolute, as the <hi>God-head,</hi> the <hi>Divine Eſſence,</hi> or <hi>Divinity,</hi> with its concomitant Attributes, where no mention is made of the Divine Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations, nor of number.</p>
               <p n="2">II. There is another manner of ſpeaking, by notional terms, as the Divines call them; ſuch are the <hi>Paternity,</hi> the <hi>Filia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> the <hi>Paſſion, Spiration,</hi> all in <hi>abſtracto,</hi> which are always to be underſtood with relation to each other, and conſtitute number.</p>
               <p n="3">III. A third way of ſpeaking is, when ſuch words are uſed as ſignifie the Divine Nature contracted with the Perſonalities, or notional Predicates, as <hi>the Father, the Son, the Holy Ghoſt,</hi> where Relations and Number are to be admitted.</p>
               <p>A third Obſervation is drawn from the two for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer,<note place="margin">3 <hi>Obſervation.</hi>
                  </note> That all the abſolute Perfections which are in the <hi>Father,</hi> are alſo in the <hi>Son,</hi> and in the <hi>Holy Ghoſt;</hi> not in equality, for where there is equality, there is alſo a relation between the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections that are equal; but the ſelf ſame numerical and individual perfections which are abſolute Predicates of the Divinity, are in all and every one of the Perſons, <hi>per communicationem idiomatum.</hi> The reaſon is, becauſe all the three Perſonalities are iden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifi'd with the Divine Nature, which is the root of all the abſolute Perfections of the Divinity; ſo theſe abſolute Perfections are alſo really identifi'd with all and every one of the Divine Perſons, according to that receiv'd Axiom of the Divines; <hi>Omnia de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit Pater Filio praeter eſſe Patrem,</hi> ſo that the Father gave the Son even the fecundity of active Spiration, whatſoever the <hi>Greeks</hi> in vain object againſt it, as I ſhall make it more largely appear in a Treatiſe of the <hi>Trinity,</hi> which I intend ſhortly to put forth. And ſo I proceed to anſwer the ill-ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed allegations of this Deiſt or Atheiſt, againſt the Orthodox Doctrin of the Church.</p>
               <p>His firſt attempt is againſt that ſaying of <hi>Athanaſius; Neither confounding the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, nor dividing the ſubſtance, for there is one Perſon of the Father, another of the Son, another of the Holy Ghoſt; but the God-head of the Father, and of the Son and Holy Ghoſt is all one.</hi> On theſe words he thus paſſeth his Cenſure: <hi>Plain as if a man ſhould ſay,</hi> Peter, James, <hi>and</hi> John, <hi>being three Perſons, are one Man, and one Man is theſe three diſtinct Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons,</hi> Peter, James, <hi>and</hi> John. A very Learned Obſervation; he compares three diſtinct human Perſons, having three di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct human Natures, with the three Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Perſons of the Sacred Trinity, where the ſame individual Divine Nature is in all three; this is ſingular, that is, numeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal; this is indiviſible, that is diviſible; this can conſtitute no more Gods but one,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:58824:6"/>that muſt conſtitute three diſtinct men. The Reaſon is obvious, becauſe the denomination of <hi>God</hi> [being a term abſolute] is taken from the Divine Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, ſo that if the Divine Nature be ſingular, the God-head muſt alſo be ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular. As the denomination of <hi>Man</hi> is taken from the Human Nature, ſo be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Human Nature is multiplied, the denomination of <hi>Man</hi> muſt alſo be multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied. How obvious is this to any vulgar Capacity? How little Reaſon had this Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor to call this Doctrin of <hi>Athanaſias,</hi> and of the Church of God, <hi>a ridiculous attempt, a barbarous indignity, a monſtrous propoſition?</hi> He might more prudently have wav'd the diſcovery of his illiterate Genius herein.</p>
               <p>Yet he goes on in the ſame ſtrain of confounding the abſolute Perfections of the Divine Eſſence, with the notional Expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of the Perſons; for on theſe Words of <hi>Athanaſius, Neither confounding the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, nor dividing the Subſtance,</hi> he adds, <hi>But how can we not confound the Perſons that have but one numerical Subſtance? And how can we not but divide the Subſtance, which we find in three diſtinct divided Perſons? There is one Perſon of the Father, another of the Son, ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the Holy Ghoſt.</hi> To which he ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyns, <hi>Then the Son is not the Father, nor is the Father the Son, nor the Holy Ghoſt either of them.</hi> 'Tis confeſt. What then? Why ſays he, <hi>If the Father is not the Son, and yet is the one true God, then the Son is not the one true God, becauſe he is not the Father.</hi> I deny this illation as falſe and nugatory on this preſent ſubject. Now to the proof, <hi>for how can the Son be the one true God, if he is not be who is the one true God?</hi> I anſwer, <hi>ſub diſtinctione;</hi> if the Son be not he who has the compleat and adequate eſſential conſtitution of the one true God, then he cannot be God, I grant it; if the Son be not another Perſon, namely the Father, and yet hath the compleat and adequate eſſenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al conſtitution of the one true God, he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be God. I deny it. The fallacy of the Author conſiſts in this, that he groſly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founds the notional and relative Predicates with the abſolute and eſſential Predicates; for conſider the ſublime Myſtery that we are upon, and what hath been ſaid above in the third Obſervation upon it, and you will find the Errour; for this Deiſt inſiſts upon two Perſons, the Father; and the Son; and ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the Father to be the one true God, he infers that therefore the Son, which is a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct Perſon, is not the one true God, and yet the ſame, though a different Perſon, yet hath all the abſolute and eſſential per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections with the Father; he hath the ſame numerical Eſſence, Nature and Divinity with the Father. Now I demand, whether it be poſſible that he ſhould have the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat and adequate eſſential Conſtitution of the God-head, and yet not be the one true God? For the God-head is ſingular, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in a number is Chimerical; you had as good tell me that one may have the ade<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quate Conſtitution of a Man, which is <hi>ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal rationale,</hi> and yet not be a man, which is impoſſible, for where there is the compleat eſſence of a thing, there is the thing it ſelf, which is nothing elfe but its compleat eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence.</p>
               <p>Then he proceeds: In the Creed <hi>the God-head of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Ghost, is all one, the Glory equal, the Majeſty co-eternal. Therefore I ask,</hi> ſays this Author, <hi>whether the Glory and Majeſty with which the Son and Spirit are Glorious and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſtical be the ſame in number with which the Father is Glorious and Majeſtical?</hi> I anſwer Affirmatively. Then it follows, ſays this Author, <hi>that the Glory and Majeſty of theſe Perſons is neither equal nor co-eternal,</hi> which he attempts to prove; becauſe equality and co-eternity import a diſtinction between the things equal and co-eternal; therefore I diſtinguiſh the ſenſe of this Illation, the Glory and Majeſty of theſe Perſons, if taken abſolutely and eſſentially, is neither equal nor co-eternal, I grant it; if taken notio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally and perſonally; I deny it. The mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of this diſtinction is cleared by the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Obſervations, for if you take them perſonally, they conſtitute number, and ground relations and cor-relations to each other; but if underſtood eſſentially and ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely, they do neither; in plain terms, the Father, Son and Holy Ghoſt, which
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:58824:6"/>are three diſtinct Perſons, are equally Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious by the ſame numerical and individual Glory which is ſingular and eſſential to the Divinity. But he replies, That in caſe the Glory of the three Perſons be numerically the ſame, then ſo are alſo all the other At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributes; whence it enſues, that there is no real diſtinction between the Father, Son and Holy Ghoſt, but are only three Names of the ſame thing without any diſtinction, as the <hi>Sebellians</hi> hold. I am ſorry that I have to deal with a Perſon ſo meanly vers'd in Divinity, as not to diſtinguiſh the At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributes of the Divinity from the notional and relative Predicates; the Attributes are ſingular, and are all communicated to every one of the Perſons, becauſe they are abſolute Predicates, but the Relations are peculiar to each Perſon; ſo the Father hath communicated to the Son all the Divine Attributes, and what elſe is peculiar to the Divine Eſſence, but hath not given him his Paternity, as is noted above, for Paternity is a relative Predicate, peculiar to one Perſon alone, and not communica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble; the ſame with proportion is to be ſaid of the Filiation, and paſſive Spiration.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>In the next place,</hi> ſays this Prophane Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beller, <hi>This Creed teaches that the Father is Incomprehenſible, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncreated, Eternal, Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, the Son is <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncreated, Eternal, Almighty</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Alſo that each of theſe Perſons by himſelf is God, and Lord, yet there are not three Gods, nor Lords, nor three Incomprehenſibles,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Now if in imitation of this, a Man ſhould have a mind to ſay the Father is a Perſon, the Son is a Perſon, the Holy Ghoſt is a Perſon, yet not three Perſons, but one Perſon; I would know why this were not as good Grammar and Arithmetick, as when</hi> Athanaſius <hi>ſays, the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is God, the Son is God, the Holy Ghoſt is God, yet not three Gods, but one God?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I anſwer, that whatever Grammar, or Arithmetick there is in it. I am ſure there is no true Divinity in it; for this Deiſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Author inſiſts here ſtill upon the ſame errour, for the word <hi>Perſon</hi> is a relative and notional expreſſion, whereof there are three in God: but the word <hi>God</hi> is an ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute and eſſential term, which is ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar, and cannot be multiplied, as hath been often reiterated in this Diſcourſe; but he demands, <hi>Doth not a man contradict himſelf, when the terms of his negation are the ſame with th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſe in his affirmation?</hi> Now for Logick. I anſwer, That two contradicto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Propoſitions ought to be <hi>ejuſdem de eo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem;</hi> that is, <hi>ejuſdem praedicati de eodem ſubjecto,</hi> as, <hi>Angelus eſt Spiritus: Angelus non eſt Spiritus. There are three Gods, there are not three Gods; there are three Perſons, there are not three Perſons,</hi> &amp;c. But where is the leaſt appearance of any Contradiction in all this?</p>
               <p>Yet to make this the more conſpicuous, I muſt take each Propoſition in pieces, and ſcan the ſeveral parts thereof according to the rates of Logick. For in theſe three Propoſitions, <hi>the Father is God, the Son is God, the Holy Ghoſt is God;</hi> the Subject of the firſt is <hi>the Father,</hi> the Subject of the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond is <hi>the Son,</hi> the Subject of the third is <hi>the Holy Ghoſt;</hi> theſe three Subjects are three diſtinct Perſon, Really different from each other. The Predicate of the firſt is <hi>God,</hi> this is an abſolute and eſſential Term, not capable of being multiplied, for it is the Deity it ſelf which is ſingular, and therefore the Predicate of the ſecond Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition, which is alſo God, muſt be the ſame Deity with the firſt, not another di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct Deity, for a ſecond <hi>God</hi> would be a meer Chimera: ſo likewiſe the Predicate of the third Propoſition is alſo <hi>God,</hi> which ſtill imports the ſame Deity, this term <hi>God</hi> not being capable of any multiplicity; ſo that the Subject of theſe three Propoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions are three different Perſons Really di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct from each other; the Predicate of the ſame three Propoſitions, which is <hi>God,</hi> hath for its Object the ſingular Eſſence of the Divine Natur, and the Propoſitions being all affirmative, do intentionally iden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifie the Deity with the ſubject of the ſame Propoſitions, which are the <hi>Father, Son,</hi> and <hi>Holy Ghoſt,</hi> as they are identifi'd <hi>a parte rei,</hi> wherein conſiſts the verity of the ſame Propoſitions.</p>
               <p>As concerning the three laſt Propoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons the caſe is very different; for in the firſt of them, which is this, <hi>the Father is a Perſon,</hi> though the Subject be the ſame as
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:58824:7"/>in the three former Propoſitions, yet the Predicate is very different; for in the firſt of theſe laſt Propoſitions the Predicate is <hi>a Perſon,</hi> a generical term, common to all Perſons; the Predicate of the ſecond is alſo <hi>a Perſon,</hi> but diſtinct from the former in application, as the Myſtery teaches; ſo likewiſe the Predicate of the third is <hi>a Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon;</hi> but theſe Propoſitions being all affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mative, cannot be verifi'd, but by apply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that generical Term <hi>a Perſon</hi> to diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent and diſtinct <hi>individuums;</hi> for an af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmative Propoſition cannot be true, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept there be an Identity between the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject and the Predicate <hi>ex parte objecti;</hi> now the Filiation is a ſingular individuation, which cannot be identifi'd with any other Perſonality, therefore the Propoſitions im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port a multiplicity of Perſons, as the three former do import a ſingularity of the Deity. Hence it is apparent, that we cannot ſay, <hi>yet not three Perſons, but one Perſon,</hi> as we ſay, <hi>yet not three Gods, but one God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>What follows in the Author, is meer ſtuff, and deſerves no further anſwer, for he goes upon a falſe ſuppoſition, which no Orthodox Chriſtian will admit; namely, that there are two ſorts of true Gods, three perſonal Gods, and beſides, one Eſſential God; whereas the Chriſtian Faith never admitted but one true God, who by his Omnipotence Created this Inferiour and Superiour Wold, and by his infinite Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence and Providence preſerveth and go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verneth all things; wherefore we deny the ſuppoſition as falſe and Heretical, as will be obvious to any who conſiders what hath been already ſaid in this Treatiſe, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally in the firſt and third Obſervation.</p>
               <p>But this great Oracle of the Deiſts goes on upon the ſubſequent paſſages of this Creed, and particularly upon theſe words: <hi>The Son is of the Father alone, not Made, nor Created, but Begotten;</hi> to which he anſwers, <hi>That if the Creed-maker had ſpoke here of the Creation of the Son by Divine Power on the Virgin</hi> Mary, <hi>it would have been true, that the Son is neither Made, nor Created, but Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten; but then the firſt part of the Article would be falſe, that the Son is of the Father alone; for he that has a Father and a Mother, is of Both. But ſince he ſpeaks of the (pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended) Eternal Generation, the latter part of the Article is falſe, and inconſiſtent with the firſt part of it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The meer explanation of the terms <hi>Made, Created,</hi> and <hi>Begotten,</hi> will evacuate this difficulty. That which is Made or Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted proceeds from the Maker or Creator, as an Effect from its Cauſe, by the media<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of a real action, or cauſalty between the cauſe and the effect; that which is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten is produced by Generation; but how ſhall we diſtinguiſh Generation from the production of the Effect from its Cauſe? I anſwer, that according to the known de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finition, admitted and approved of in the Schools of Philoſophers and Divines: Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration is <hi>Origo viventis à vivente, à principio conjuncto, in Similitudinem naturae.</hi> Now to admit a real Action or Cauſality between the Father and the Son in the Eternal Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration of the Divine Word, were to make a change in the Divine Eſſence, <hi>ad intra,</hi> of that immutable God that can ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit of no change. Whence it unavoida<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably follows, that the Eternal Son of God is neither Made, nor Created; but how how then can we make it appear that he is Begotten? I anſwer, becauſe he is produ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced by Generation, according to the defini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion given; for he is produced by the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Underſtanding, as related to all Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures poſſible, by a clear and conſpicuous repreſentation, but eſpecially a lively I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage of all the Perfections of the Divinity, which makes him to be <hi>in ſimilitudinem na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turae,</hi> as I ſhall more largely explicate and prove in the <hi>Treatiſe of the Trinity,</hi> which I intend ſhortly to bring to light. But to talk of a <hi>Mother</hi> (as this Author doth) is an impertinent indignity offer'd to the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Word, and ſavours too much of the mean thoughts of the ignorant Vulgar.</p>
               <p>Next in the <hi>Athanaſian</hi> Creed follows, that <hi>the Holy Ghoſt is of the Father, and of the Son, neither Made, nor Created, nor Begotten, but Proceeding.</hi> Here this Deiſt Cavils firſt with the Holy Ghoſt's proceeding from the Son, contrary to the Tenet of the <hi>Greek</hi> Church, for which he cites that Text of Scripture, <hi>John</hi> 15.26. <hi>When the Comforter
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:58824:7"/>is come, which I will ſend unto you from the Father, even the Spirit of Truth, which pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedeth from the Father, he ſhall teſtifie of me.</hi> Doth this Text prove that the Holy Ghoſt doth not proceed from the Son? it only aſſerts that the Holy Ghoſt proceeds from the Father, which we all grant, but whether or no it proceedeth alſo from the Son, it doth not determine; but I ſhall prove this at large in my <hi>Treatiſe of the Trinity.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly, he ſays</hi> (ſubjoyns this Author) <hi>that the Holy Ghoſt is not begotten, but pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding;</hi> yet he alledgeth that it is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed by the moſt Learned Trinitarians, that <hi>Begotten</hi> and <hi>Proceeding</hi> differ nothing at all; But I would fain know who thoſe Learned Trinitarians are; for it is well known that the ſecond Perſon of the Trinity, therefore is Begotten, becauſe he is produced by the Underſtanding, which repreſents the Deity, and the Creatures poſſible, ſo that by the internal vertue of his production, he is intended to be <hi>in ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militudinem</hi> [whence he is called the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Word] <hi>naturae,</hi> whereas the Holy Ghoſt proceeds by the Will, which is no repreſentative Power, but be proceeds by an act of Love of the ſame Divinity; who doth not ſee that theſe two are far different from each other? and this clearly ſolves that frivolous Diſcourſe which follows; that in counting right we ſhould ſay two Father, two Sons, and three Holy Ghoſts, or Spirits; for which ſaying there is no ground at all, as appears by the difference given between <hi>Begotten,</hi> and <hi>Proceeding.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Next in the Creed follows, <hi>None is afore, or after other; none greater, or leſs than an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Yet the Son himſelf ſaith,</hi> John 14.28. <hi>the Father is greater than 1.</hi> I anſwer, That the <hi>Son</hi> ſays not this of his Divinity, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Hypoſtatically united to fleſh, he ſpoke it when he was in fleſh of his Humani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; <hi>none is afore or after other.</hi> I ask, ſays this Deiſt, <hi>whether the Son doth not, as he is a Son, derive both Life and God-head from the Father?</hi> I anſwer affirmatively. But, ſays he; <hi>if the Father gave to the Son Life and Godhead, he muſt have both before he could communicate or give either of them to the Son.</hi> I anſwer, All this argues only <hi>prioritatem originis,</hi> for as much as the Father was the Origine of all that is in the Son, but all was done from Eternity; ſo there could be no <hi>prioritas temporis,</hi> for before Eternity there was no time; neither could there be any <hi>prioritas naturae,</hi> ſuch as there is in a Cauſe in reſpect of its Effect, ſince the Father was not the Cauſe, and the Son the Effect, for all Cauſes produce their Effects by the Mediation of an Action, whereof the Cauſe is the Origine, and the Effects is the term, wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ch receives the acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and ſubjects it in it ſelf, as the Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophers teach: Now the Eternal Son of God was produced by an act of the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Underſtanding, which doth not ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate by acts diſtinct from it ſelf, as Men and Angels do; but all acts of the Divine Intellect and Will have a real identity with the Divine Nature and Eſſence of God, as the Divines teach; for elſe if God ſhould underſtand by diſtinct acts, thoſe acts muſt inform the Divine Underſtanding, which would make a change in God, and ſo deſtroy his Immutability, as is apparent. The ſame with proportion is to be ſaid of the Holy Ghoſt, who proceeds by an act of Love from the Divine Will, no leſs than that act of the Divine Intellect produces the Divine Word, or its Hypoſtaſis.</p>
               <p>With what reaſon, now, can this Author ſtill go on in his wilful ignorance? He often ſaith that this Creed contains many Contradictions, and as many Impoſſibilities as Trabſubſtantiation, and yet in all his Diſcourſe, he hath not alledged two Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions with a contradictory oppoſition which follows out of the Doctrin of this Creed; nay, I confidently aſſert, that nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he, nor any of his Sect, can alledge any one contradiction iſſuing from the ſame Doctrin. Let the pretended con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradiction be aſſigned, and we are ready to anſwer it, and to diſcover its fallacy; but to blunder and vaper as this Author does, that there are Two Fathers, Two Sons, and Three Holy Ghoſts, and yet prove nothing of all this, is not to proceed like a Scholar, much leſs like a Divine, but is wholly loſs of time.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="14" facs="tcp:58824:8"/>How often muſt I inculcate this Ortho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dox Truth? That in the ineffable Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery of the Divine Trinity, the characte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſtical notion of the Father is his innaſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility, together with his paternity and fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cundity of active ſpiration; of the Son is his filiation and fecundity of active ſpirati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; of the Holy Ghoſt, is his paſſive Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration alone; Theſe Three Perſons, as they mutually are correlatives to each other, ſo they are really diſtinct from each other; they are capable of Multipli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, and conſtitute a number. The Father hath in himſelf (beſides the relative Predicates) all the abſolute Predicates and Perfections that are contained in the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Nature and Eſſence, all the Attributes of the Divinity. The Father hath Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municated to the Son all the abſolute Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections of the Divine Nature, and the notional Predicate of active Spiration. To the Holy Ghoſt, the Father and the Son have communicated all the Divinity, with all the abſolute Attributes and Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections thereunto belonging.</p>
               <p>So that although theſe three Perſons are three in number, yet the Divinity of them all is the ſelf-ſame individual and ſingular Deity; for the ſame Divine Nature that is in the Father, is alſo in the Son, and Holy Ghoſt. Now this Author would have us to multiply the Divinity as the Perſons are multiplied, thereby to lead his Reader in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a Labyrinth of Errors, by acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing more Gods than one; which in effect is no better than rank Paganiſm. Muſt we follow the conduct of his wild Genius, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he pretends to Demonſtrations, which in effect are meer Improbabilities; or ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>here to thoſe Sacred Truths which are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered to us by holy Writ, and are backt by Divine Authority? But let us proceed with him to the Incarnation of the Divine Word.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Athanaſian</hi> Creed from hence pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds to the Incarnation of the Divine Word; thus, <hi>The right Faith is, that we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve and confeſs, that our <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ord Jeſus Chriſt the Son of God is both God and Man.</hi> To which words this Author replies, <hi>That then the Lord Chriſt is two Perſons, for as he is God, he is the ſecond Perſon of the Trinity; and as he is man (a perfect man) he is alſo a Perſon, for a Rational Soul vitally united to a Humane Body, is a Perſon.</hi> I anſwer, that a Rational Soul vitally united to a Humane Body is the compleat Nature of a Man, compleat I ſay, <hi>ratione naturae,</hi> but to be compleat alſo <hi>ratione Perſonae,</hi> you muſt add to this compleat Nature a <hi>ſubſiſtentia,</hi> which makes up the compleat Suppoſitum, or Hypoſtaſis of a man <hi>ratione perſonae.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But in Chriſt there was no need of this Humane <hi>ſubſiſtentia,</hi> for the Divine Word aſſumed the compleat Humane Nature, not the Human Perſon, as <hi>Neſtorius</hi> ſaid; for the Humanity of Chriſt ſubſiſts by the Perſonality of the Divine Word, which ſupplies abundantly all defects, and functi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons which the Humane Perſonality would exerciſe, were it preſent; ſo that the Humane Perſonality would be ſuperfluous in Chriſt, and of no uſe at all.</p>
               <p>To what he adds, <hi>[viz.] Let the</hi> Atha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſians <hi>then Confeſs that Chriſt was not God, which is the truth.</hi> Here he plainly profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth his Error, and flatly denies the Divini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Chriſt. It is not my deſign to prove at large in this ſhort Treatiſe, the Divinity of Chriſt, which the Divines have effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally prov'd in the matter of Incarnation. I ſhall therefore only hint at ſome Parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars: As the fulfilling of the Prophecies of the Old Prophets, the Teſtimony of the Eternal Father in a Voice from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven: <hi>This is my Beloved Son, in whom I am well pleaſed;</hi> the often aſſeveration of Chriſt himſelf, confirmed by many ſtrange and prodigious Miracles, and ſealed by his Death, the Reluctancy of Nature at his Crucifixion, his Reſurrection after Death, which none could effect but by the mighty hand of the Omnipotent; the Univerſal atteſtation of all the Apoſtles, in Confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation whereof they all ſacrificed their Lives, with other pregnant motives con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in the Sacred Word of God, which are too prolix for this ſhort Treatiſe; all which being duly prondered and conſidered, are able to convince, not only an indiffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent judgment, but alſo the moſt obſtinate and perverſeſt judgment that can be, if it
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:58824:8"/>be ſwayed by Reaſon, and work them into a ſtedfaſt belief of the Divinity of Chriſt; wherefore I ſhall wave (in this place) any further dilatation of my Diſcourſe upon this Subject.</p>
               <p>Now we proceed to examine the Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtatical Union between the Divinity and Humanity of Chriſt, how we can make it out, that any Union can be of that Nature as to unite two Natures, whereof the one is Infinite, and the other Finite? for the <hi>Athanaſian</hi> Creed aſſerts, that though <hi>Chriſt be God and Man, yet he is not two, but one Chriſt; one, not by Converſion of the Godhead into fleſh, but by taking the Manhood into God; one, not by confuſion of ſubſtance, but by <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity of Perſon; for as the reaſonable Soul and fleſh is one Man, ſo God and Man is one Chriſt.</hi> Againſt this the Deiſt argues, that <hi>in the Perſonal <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion is between Finite and Infinite, which is impoſſible. For we muſt either ſuppoſe that Finite and Infinite are commenſurate, that is, equal, which every one knows is falſe; or that the Finite is <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nited but to ſome part of the Infinite, and is disjoyned from the reſt.</hi> A ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Learned Reflection! For who is igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant of Gods Eternity, and Immenſity, or Ubiquity? Which are two of the Divine Attributes. All Created Durations flow ſucceſſively by parts, whereof none are at any time in being, but only thoſe that are preſent; for to day, yeſterday is paſt, its duration is deſtroyed, and to morrow is not yet come, its duration is not yet produced; and ſo of all Created Durations; whether this be done only by indiviſible inſtances, as <hi>Zeno</hi> Taught, or by indiviſible inſtances, and diviſible parts, which was <hi>Ariſtotle</hi>'s Opinion in his Treatiſe <hi>De continuo Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſivo.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But God's Eternity is far different; for this admits of no parts, but is one indivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible duration, eſſentially determin'd to co-exiſt to all Created duration, and Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity; there are no parts deſtroyed, and others to come, not yet in being; for by the ſame indiviſible duration whereby the Divinity exiſted from Eternity, he exiſts now, and exiſted yeſterday, and ſhall exiſt to morrow, and ever, and yet loſes no parts of its duration, becauſe it hath none. Hence <hi>Boetius,</hi> and with him the current of Divines, gives this definition of it, <hi>Aeternitas Dei eſt indeterminabilis vitae, tota ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mul &amp; perfect a poſſeſſio;</hi> a perfect poſſeſſion of an endleſs life, altogether, <hi>tota ſimul,</hi> not by parts, as it is in all Created durations.</p>
               <p>The Immenſity of God Conſiſts in this, that he is eſſentially determin'd to all Created ſpace, whenſoever or whereſoever it exiſts; ſo that God by his Immenſity, without any parts, is actually preſent to all Created ſpace or place, how diſtant ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever the parts of ſpace are from one an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other; to which God correſponds not by ſeveral parts, but by an increate definitive ubication, whereby he is <hi>torus in toto, &amp; totus in qualibet parte;</hi> all the Deity is in all the ſpace, and all the Deity is in every part and particle of ſpace, whereſoever, or whenſoever exiſtent; as an Angel, which is indiviſible, is in the place which he Occupies by a definitive ubication; for the whole Angel is at the ſame time in all the ſpace, and the whole Angel at the ſame time is in every part and particle of the ſame ſpace; ſo is the Soul of Man, which is likewiſe indiviſible, in a humane Body; for the whole Soul is in all the Body, and the whole Soul is in every part and par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle of the Body; ſo that the Soul exiſts in the Body by a definitive ubication, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as the Body at the ſame time exiſts in ſpace by a circumſcriptive ubication, whereby its parts are collocated ſo, as that one part of the Body correſponds to one part of the ſpace, and another part of the Body to another part of the ſpace. Now to the Objection.</p>
               <p>The Humanity of Chriſt is conſtituted in place by a circumſcriptive ubication, where the Divinity, the whole Divine Word is intimately preſent to him; what commenſuration more than this is neceſſary for a conjunction between the Humanity, and the Divine Word? For that the Divine Word is in all places elſe, by his immenſity, is impertinent to this caſe, as long as the Divine Word is in irely and intimately preſent to the whole Humanity, where the Hypoſtatical Union may exerciſe its functi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:58824:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>of connecting the Humanity to the Divinity; for it is too groſs an imaginati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Divinity, that part of it ſhould correſpond to the Humanity, and part not; for in the Divine Nature there are no parts, but all is indiviſible.</p>
               <p>Now for the Hypoſtatical Union, it is ſubjected in the Humanity, and terminated to the Divinity, or Divine Word; for the Eſſence of God is uncapable of receiving any thing diſtinct from it ſelf. And 'tis in vain to tell me that this includes as many Contradictions as Mr. <hi>Johnſon</hi>'s Treatiſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Tranſubſtantiation doth. Produce thoſe Contradictions that this Myſtery doth include, and we ſhall uſe our endeavour to ſolve them.</p>
               <p>The ſecond Objection is grounded upon an Error, that the Union between the Divine Word, and the Humanity of Chriſt connects two Perſons, as <hi>Neſtorius</hi> would have it; but this error is already exploded. But it is in vain to ſift all the extent of Nature, for a parity to the Hypoſtatical Union of the Divine Word to the Humani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Chriſt, which is tranſcendent above all the power of Nature, where the two diſtinc: Lives, Memories, Reaſons and free Wills are no obſtacle at all to it; for theſe two Natures do not hinder the Operations and Functions of each other.</p>
               <p>Thus I have run through all the Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, pretended Contradictions, and Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſibilities, which this Author alledgeth againſt thoſe Sacred Myſteries of Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity; wherein I have endeavoured to give a ſatisfactory ſolution to them all. Tho' he hath inſiſted upon ſuch Myſteries as are eaſieſt to be impugned, and hardeſt to be defended. For they are ſuch as are deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to us by the Sacred Scripture, as back'd by Divine Authority, and are not within the reach of Natural Reaſon to demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate. 'For it were no leſs than a temera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious preſumption in any man that ſhould attempt to prove any one of theſe Myſteries by Natural Reaſon; Myſteries that are ſo ſublime, and elevated above the reach of Natural Reaſon, that they are not pervi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to the Wit or Capacity either of Man or Angel; which if Faith did not teach, Reaſon could not explicate; ſo that we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive them from Holy Writ (as atteſted by Divine Authority) with great ſubmiſſion and veneration, and are ready to vindicate them from all pretended impoſſibilities, Contradictions, and other Difficulties which the <hi>Mahometans, Jews, Deists, Atheiſts,</hi> or other Infidels can muſter up againſt them. And I hope in this ſhort Treatiſe I have not ſwerved from the receiv'd and approv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Doctrin of the Reformed Proteſtant Church of <hi>England,</hi> to whoſe Authority and Correction I ſubmit.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
